Guide to the Yale Music Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Yale Music, Series I
  - BULLDOG and other Yale songs arranged into one choral presentation. With words and music, Author unidentified. Undated. 12p. photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Yale Music, Series II
  - A SONG ON VACATION. Words by Daniel Tillotson (Yale 1798). Music by David B.Wilcockson (Yale 1798). Yale College, January 1, 1796. Photostat. 1p. First line: "Ye sons of Yale with visage pale, Come join the happy chorus; Vacation's near our hearts to cheer, When girls & wine shall moor us." (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - PARTING HYMN, 1830. Words only, by W. R. Morris (Yale 1830). 1p. First line: "From thy holy habitation, Throned in radiant glory there, Listen to our supplication, Father, hear thy children's prayer." (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - LES CHARMES DE NEW HAVEN [PHOTOSTATS] by Charles M. King, 1835-1840 (Box 3, Folder 2a)
  - PARTING HYMN: BY A MEMBER OF THE GRADUATING CLASS. No music. Yale College, Theological Seminary, August 14, 1838. Begins: "Farewell! the hour has come! Each lingering heart breathes o'er this cherished home the last sigh, ere we part." 1p. (Box 3, Folder 2a)
  - SONGS AND TRANSLATIONS. By Lucius W. Fitch (Yale 1840.) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - GOOSEY, GOOSEY, GANDER, OR THE FIREMEN AND THE STUDENTS. A NEW GLEE, TO BE SUNG ON THE STATE HOUSE STEPS, AT THE NEXT FIREMEN'S PARADE, BY THE BEETHOVEN CLUB. THE EDITOR OF THE YALE BANNER BEATING TIME WITH THE JAWBONE OF AN ASS. By Edward W. Gilman (Yale 1843). 1841. 1p. Begins: "Goosey, Goosey, Gander, whither shall I wander? Up stairs, down stairs, thro' the College chamber." 6 copies. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - THE GATHERED ALUMNI OF YALE, TO THEIR ALMA MATER; BY A GRADUATE OF 1794. Sung at the Meeting of the Alumni, August 19th, 1846. (by Ezekiel Bacon or Elijah Bates. initials. E. B. are at the end of the song). No music. Begins: "Full many lustrums in their course their cycling round have run, Since here beneath thy plastic hand life's labors were begun." 1p. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ODES SUNG AT THE MEETING OF THE ALUMNI OF YALE COLLEGE, August 18th and 19th, 1847. Ode I - The Fraternal Meeting, by a graduate of 1794 (signed E.B. as above), Begins: "From Maine's bleak snow-capped mountains." Ode II - Salve, Magna Parens! by a graduate of 1840 (signed D.M., could be Daniel March, or DeWitt C. Morris). Begins: "To thee O Alma Mater!" Ode III - The Parting by a graduate of 1794 (also signed E.B.), Begins: "Can ancient friendships be forgot." (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - J.M. Hubbard (Yale 1859?), photograph, letter, and two songs: "'TWAS OFF THE BLUE CANARIES, OR MY LAST CIGAR" (1848), and "ROBIN RED-BREAST" (1859). (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - COMMENCEMENT CONCERT. July 29, 1852. Words only. 1p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SOPHOMORES' SONG OF VICTORY. October 13, 1852. Words only. 1p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - PARTING ODE. By Benjamin K. Phelps (Yale 1853). Music by J. Sumner Smith (Yale 1853). Words only. No imprint (1853). Words begin: "Listen, brothers, to the echoes falling soft into the heart." 1p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - PARTING ODE. By Lewis Ledyard Weld (Yale 1854). Music by Adrian Van Sinderen (Yale 1854). Words only. 1p. Words begin: "I saw two rivers onward run." Pasted on verso of song above. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SONGS FOR THE BIENNIAL JUBILEE OF THE CLASS OF FIFTY-FIVE. Yale, July 22, 1853. Words only. 3p. & title page. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SONGS FOR PRESENTATION DAY. June 15, 1853. Words only. 3p. and title page. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SONGS FOR THE BIENNIAL JUBILEE OF THE CLASS OF FIFTY-SIX. Yale, July 21, 1854. Words only. 3p. & title page. 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SOPHOMORE JUBILEE SONG. AIR - "O SUSANNA!" By J.K. Lombard. Words only. 1p. Words begin: "Ye bold and merry sons of Yale." 4 copies., 1854 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - GAUDEAMUS. A Latin song, sung by German Students. Arranged as a Solo, and also a Quartet for two Tenors and two Basses, by Richard Storrs Willis. 2p. each version. With English translation which begins: "Let us then, while juveniles, Know no joys restraining." 3 copies., 1855 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Article from Yale Alumni Weekly "GAUDEAMUS IGITUR. Some facts concerning the origin of a famous song - words in the thirteenth and eighteenth centuries.", undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - THE SHEEPSKIN. An American Student-song: as sung at Yale College on "presentation day." Arranged by Richard Storrs Willis. 4p. Words begin: "When first I saw a "Sheepskin," In Prex's hand I spied it." 2 copies., 1855 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SONGS FOR PRESENTATION DAY. June 13, 1855. Words only. 3p. & title page. 4 copies. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SONGS FOR PRESENTATION DAY, CLASS OF 1856, June 18, 1856. Words only. 3p. & title page. 3 copies. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Song sheet from Class Supper, class of 1860. August 9, 1858. Words only. 1p. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - DESCRIPTION OF THE SEASONS, An Oratorio composed by Joseph Haydn. Program of performance by the Mendelssohn Society of New Haven. Jan. 27, 1864. 7p. & title page. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SONGS FOR THE SECOND ANNUAL SUPPER OF THE YALE ALUMNI ASSOCIATION OF BOSTON AND VICINITY. Jan. 28, 1867. Words only. 3p. & title page. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SONGS FOR THE TRIENNIAL MEETING, Class of 1864. July 17, 1867. 5p. & title page. No words. 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Advertisement for Carmina Yalensia ., Yale song book, 1867. 1p. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Song sheet from Yale College Alumni dinner, 1872. Words only. 1p. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - BOYS AT YALE. By N.W. Williams, 1887. Words only. 1p. Words begin: "Welcome Yale men!" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - THE GLORY OF OLD YALE, A SONG FOR ALL DEGREES. By N. W. Williams, 1887. Words only. 1p. Words begin: "Go, search the east and search the west." (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - RING! RING! OF LIBERTY AND PEACE! Words by Henry B. Carrington (Yale 1845). Arranged by Launce Knight. Boston, 1889. 3p. Words begin: "Ye sons of this grand land of liberty." (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - YALE SONGS OF THE NINETIES. Bound volume of songs collected by Lee McClung (Yale 1892). 135p., 1890's (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - THE BLUE OF YALE. Words by Frederick A. Stokes. Music by Ciro Pinsuti. (Stokes - Yale 1879). 1890. 2p. Words begin: "To the glorious name of Yale our homage bring." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 'TIS OUR LAST GATHERING. By B. Jepson. 1892. 3p. Words begin: "'Tis our last gathering as a class." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - BRIGHT AND HAPPY ARE THE YEARS. By B. Jepson. 1893. 3p. 2 copies. Words begin: "Bright and Happy are the years, which together we have passed." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SHONINGER MUSICAL MONTHLY. New Haven, October, 1893. No. 112. 16p. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - THE WINNING TOUCHDOWN: A FOOTBALL SONG. Words by Juliet Wilbor Tompkins. Music by Gilbert Tompkins. New York, 1895. 6p. Removed from MUMSEYS MAGAZINE July 1896. Words begin: "Captain damaged and six to four; We the under side of the score." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SONGS. 1898. Six songs of Psi Upsilon. 8p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - BRAVE MOTHER YALE. Words by Charles Edmund Merrill (Yale 1898). Music by Thomas G, Shepard. New Haven, 1899. 4p. and title page with photograph of Phelps Hall and statement: Sung by the Yale University Glee Club. Words begin: "Fairer than love of woman, Stronger than pride of gold." (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - LOIN DU PAYS. By Rodolphe Berger. Paris, 1899. 2p. No words. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - A KNOT OF BLUE: FOR THE BOYS OF YALE. Words by Samuel Mintern Peck. Music by R.S. Bradway. 1900. 2p. with explanatory letter by Bradway. Note: Refer to song no. 21, an earlier version with music by Phillips. Letter states that Peck was a Yale graduate, but there is no record of his attendance at Yale. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - YALE SONGS FOR HARVARD-YALE MATCH, Nov. 24, 1900. Song sheet, 1p. Words only. Accompanied by letter. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - ELI'S SLEDGEHAMMER. Author unknown. Dated Nov., 1901, 1p. Words only. Words begin: "For old Yale has got a brand-new sledge for Princeton/Harvard." (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - FOOTBALL SONGS. 1901/1902. Song sheet, 1p. Words only. Note: "These are to be learned by every undergraduate." 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - FOOTBALL SONGS, 1902. Song sheet, 1p. Words only. 6 copies. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - HARVARD SONGS. 1902. Song sheet, 2p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - YALE SONGS. Commencement week, 1902. 7p. & title page. words only. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - FOOTBALL SONGS. 1903. Song sheet, 1p. Words only. 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - FOOTBALL SONGS. 1904. 4p. Words only. 6 copies, one with additional, typed page. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - BASEBALL SONGS. 1905. 3p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1905 SONG BOOK. Dedicated to the class of 1905 by Frank Squier, 1905. 14p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - DEAR OLD YALE (BRIGHT COLLEGE YEARS). Words by H.S. Durand '81. Music by Carl Wilhelm. New York, 1906. 1p. and title page. Explanatory letter. 3 copies. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - THE SPIRIT OF OLD YALE. By Chester Wolcott Lyman (Yale 1882). 1p. Words only. Words begin: "What inspirations e'er pervade.", 1906 June 26 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - MOTHER OF MEN. Heald Prize Song for. Music by Seth Bingham (Yale 1904), words by W. Brian Hooker (Yale 1902). New Haven, 1907. 1p. Words begin: "Mother of Men, grown strong in giving Honor to them thy lights have led." 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - UNIVERSITY CLUB SONGS. 12p. & title page. Words only., 1908 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - MY LADYE'S HEART: A SONG OF YALE. Words by Lilla Thomas Elder. Music by Harriet Burdett Wills. Boston. 4p. & title page. Words begin: "She may carry the color of Harvard in her kissable crimson lips.", 1908 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - OLD COLLEGE SONGS, reprinted from The Century Magazine. 8P. with title page and illustrations. Includes "Fair Harvard," "I-eel," "Old Nassau.", 1908 June (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - HAIL! YALE, THY SONS ARE WE. Words and Music by Leonard M. Thomas (Yale 1901). no place. 1p. Words begin: "Hail! Yale, Thy sons are we, proud in thy power." 2 copies., 1912 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - GOOD NIGHT HARVARD. By Douglas S. Moore (Yale 1915, Mus. B 1917). Original Manuscript. 3p. & title page. Words begin: "Good night, poor Harvard. Harvard, good night." Accompanied by two explanatory letters., 1913 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - YALE SONGS TRANSLATED INTO YIDDISH. By Hirsh L. Gordon. (Yale 1922 Ph.D.)..No music. I. DEAR OLD YALE. II. BZT BZT (A whistling tune). published in DER AMERIKANER, A national Jewish Weekly Devoted to Science, Art & Literature. Volume XVIII, No. 30. New York. 2p., 1920 July 23 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - CHEERING FOR THE OLD YALE BLUE. March Song. Words and Music by W. Kyle Sheffield (Yale 1908 Sheff). New Haven, 1921. 3p. & title page. Words begin: "For God, for country and dear old Yale. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - SOME "SMOKER" SONGS FOR YALE ALUMNI. Associated Southern Yale Clubs, Washington D.C., May 27-28, 1921. 4p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - SONG BOOK. Harvard songs for twentieth celebration, 1902-1922. 6p. Words only. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - THE HOUSE OF OLD YALE. Words and Music by Henry S. Durand (Yale 1881). New York. 1p. photocopy of original manuscript (2 copies). Each is autographed by composer. Words begin: "Every blessing entail, on the House of Old Yale.", 1923 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper article from The Springfield Republican (?) "'EILI EILI' PLAYED BEFORE U.S. COURT.", 1925 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Song Sheet. 1p. typed: BINGO ELI YALE; GOOD-NIGHT, HARVARD; BULLDOG; BOOLA; MARCH DOWN THE FIELD., 1926 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - LONG CHEER. Words by William B. Chappell (Yale). Music by W. Kyle Sheffield (Yale 1908 Sheff.). Arranged by L. Bykowski. New Haven, 1927. 3p. & illustrated title page. Words begin: "Brek-ek-ek-ex Co-ax Co-ax." 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - THE YALE BLUES. Fox-Trot Song. With ukulele arrangement. Words by Collie Knox. Music by Vivian Ellis. London & New York. 3p., illustrated title page, & 1p. of instructions of how to dance the Yale Blues by Cecil H. Taylor. Words begin: "A boy once went to College and studied 'Blues' all day, not quite the sort of knowledge, for which good fathers pay." Chorus: "They say the Yale is like the walk of any snail.", 1927 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Yale University Band at the Yale Club, New York City. Program/song sheet. 1p. Words only. 2 copies., 1927 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper article New Haven Register, "COMPOSER OF POPULAR YALE AIRS LOCAL MAN.", 1927 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - WHAT SHALL WE DO WITH A DRUNKEN SAILOR? Traditional Sea Chantey Freely arranged by Marshall Bartholomew (Yale 1907 Sheff.). No. 14 of the YALE GLEE CLUB SERIES, Selected, Arranged and Edited by Marshall Bartholomew. New York. 6p. & title page., 1930 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - LUX ET VERITAS (YALE REUNION SONG). To Yale 1901. Words by Arthur L. Griffiths (Yale 1901) and Leonard M. Thomas (Yale 1901). Music by Leonard M. Thomas. [1931] 2p. & title page with statement: Composed and written for the thirtieth reunion of the class of 1901, Yale. Words begin: "Fair memories of college days, with friendships strong and hale." (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - A CENTURY OF YALE SONGS. By Marshall Bartholomew, 1907 Sheff. Article from Yale Alumni Weekly, 1933 April 21 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - MUSIC OF NEW YALE SONG. For word competition. Music by Stanleigh P. Friedman (Yale 1905). no place. 1p. 3 copies., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - SONS OF YALE. Yale Marching Song. Dedicated to Francis Gordon Brown. Yale 1901. Words by Paul Gilbert (Yale 1901). Music by Leonard Thomas (Yale 1901). New York. 3p. & title page. Words begin: "Let flourish of trumpet and voices unite to herald our pride in Eli's honor'd name and might.", 1936 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - TRUE-BLUE ELIHU. Words by Fairfax Downey (Yale 1916). Music by Arthur. Hall (Yale 1924 Music). New York. 2p. & title page. Copy autographed by Downey, Hall, & Marshall Bartholomew., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - THE WHIFFENPOOF SONG (BAA! BAA! BAA!).By Meade Minnigerode (Yale 1910), Georges. Pomeroy (Yale 1910), and Tod B. Galloway. Revision by Rudy Vallee (Yale 1927). New York 4p. & illustrated title page with photograph of Harkness Tower. Words begin: "To the tables down at Mory's.", 1936 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - YALE SONGS. Pamphlet, Words only, 2 copies., 1936 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letter and advertisement for Hotel Lincoln., 1936 December 7 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - THE BATTLE OF THE BOOKS. Words by Fairfax Downey (Yale 1916). Music by Arthur Hall (Yale 1924 Music). 10p. Facsimile copy autographed by Marshall Bartholomew, 1938. Words begin: "Draw nigh all Yale men who would dwell in "Veritas et Lux" and hear the tale we have to tell of the "Battle of the Books." (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - SO WE'LL SAY TO YOU GOOD-NIGHT. March. Words and Music by Charles Henry Marsh. New Haven, 1938. 3p. & title page. Words begin: "When Yale and Harvard play football the arguments begin." (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - WE'VE GOT A LOT IN COMMON. From the Yale Dramat Production "1066 and All that." Words and Music by Perry Lafferty (Yale 1938 Music). New Haven, 1938. 4p. & illustrated title page. Chorus: "We've got a lot in common, like birds and bees." (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - HAIL YALE '29. Class Song. Words and Music by Harold J. Rome (Yale 1929). New York, 1939. 2p. & illustrated title page. Words begin: "Hail to the class of twenty-nine in all its splendor." 2 copies. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Advertisement for Yale Record Albums. 1960's. New Haven., 1940's (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - THE MEMORY OF OLD YALE. Words and Music by Dick Brecker (Yale 1943). New Haven, 1942. 2p. & title page with statement: This song will be played by the Yale Band and sung by the Yale Cheering Section between the first and second quarters of today's game with Dartmouth. Words begin: "What is nearer, what is dearer to the hearts of men than the memory of old Yale." 4 copies. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letter from Allan M. Hirsh (Yale 1901), May 29, 1945,concerning THE UNDERTAKER SONG (1900). (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - AS FRESHMEN FIRST WE CAME TO SHEFF. Words by D. Dudley Brill (Yale 1919 Sheff). No music: to be sung to the tune, "Mademoiselle from Armentieres."[1946] 1p. mimeographed sheet. Words begin: "Oh, As Freshmen first we came to Sheff, very young." (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - DADDY IS A YALE MAN. Words and Music by David Lippincott (Yale 1949). Copyright 1946. Photocopy of publication in the YALE RECORD issue for Princeton game, 1947. 2p. with. illustration and statement: As introduced by the Whiffenpoofs. Words begin: "As the New Haven train left Grand Central, a young girl climbed on with her kids." (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letter. Inquiry about "The Whistlepup Song.", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - HAIL TO YALE. 25th Reunion Song - Class of 1924. Words by Frank Field (Yale 1924 Sheff.). Music by Charlie O'Hearn (Yale 1924 Sheff.). [1949] 2p. Words begin: "Hail to Yale and its most remarkable class, they gave us Lux and occasional Veritas." (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - REUNION. Words and Music by W. Kyle Sheffield (Yale 1908 Sheff.). New York, 1952. 2p. & title page. Words begin: "Reunion, Reunion, Reunion! This magic word recalls the days we have reviewed." 3 copies. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper article from Christian Science Monitor, Jan. 3, 1952: "Yale songs of the Sixties." (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - THE RED HERRING. Arranged by Fenno Heath (Yale 1949). New York, 1953. 11p. and title page. Words begin: "What d'ye think I have made with my red herring's head?" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Advertisement for yale record albums. 1956. New Haven (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - BLADDERBALL VICTORY SONG. YALE DAILY NEWS. To besung to the tune of "Tom Dooley." 1959. 1p. mimeo-graphed sheet. Chorus: "We are the Virgin Goal Line, Holding our heads up high.", 1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - CHANSONS DE FOOTBALL DE YALE. French translations of Yale football songs. undated. 1p. typed, with Professor Jackson written at bottom. (Joseph F. Jackson was Professor of Romance Languages at Yale in the 1930's). No. music. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - LITORIA. Words and music by unidentified author. Undated. 1p. Printed with other Yale Glee Club songs including SHOOL, THE POPE HE LEADS A JOLLY LIFE, CHURCH IN THE WILDWOOD, A.B.C., and THE WHIZZ-FISH. Words begin: "Yale College is a jolly home, Swedelewedumbum." (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - List of "College Song Writers." 2p., undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Yale songs, undated. Most with words only. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Music missing from collection
    - LITORIA! LITORIA! As sung by the students of Yale College New York, 1859.[Student's songs, no. 8]
    - I AM A YALE GIRL. Words & music by Reese Cassard. Baltimore Md., 1896
    - "MISS HARVARD OF YALE." Words by Andrew B. Sterling; music by Harry Von Tilzer. New York, 1897
    - POLLY! OR EYES OF OLD YALE BLUE. Words by Roberta F. Watterson. Music by David Smith (Yale 1900). New Haven, 1903. 3p. & illustrated title page. Chorus: "And while now I drink to Polly, All ye sons of Eli true, Come and drink ye to the lassies who have eyes of Old Yale Blue."
    - BINGO ELI YALE. Words & Music by Cole Porter (Yale 1913). New York, 1910. 4p. & illustrated title page. Words begin: "Bingo, Bingo, Bingo, Bingo, Bingo, what's the lingo?"
      General
      See: The Cole Porter Collection, MS 82, Music Library, Yale University.
- "Ditirambo dal Bacco in Toscano" di Francesco Redi, 1929; Accession 19ND-A-509
  - Francesco Redi, "Ditirambo dal Bacco in Toscano", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copiato per mano di D.V.T., Jr. per il gentil diporto di T.S., amico collega suo, pio aderente di Bacco in esilio, a festa di natale.
- Manuscript for "Bright College Years", 1881; Accession 2002-A-132
  - "Bright College Years" by Henry Durand, 1881 (Box 1)
- "Mother Of Men" Yale's New Song, as printed in the Live Wire, circa 1902; Accession 2005-A-125
  - "Mother of Men" Yale's New Song, as printed in the Live Wire, circa 1902 (Box 1)
- "Glory for Yale (Yale March and One Step)", circa 1919; Accession 2008-A-103
  - "Glory for Yale (Yale March and One Step)", circa 1919 (Box 1)
- Sheet music for "Yale March & Two step Boola", 1901; Accession 2008-A-103
  - Sheet music for "Yale March and Two step Boola", 1901 (Box 1)